all right
[Music]
although it's known that plant-based
foods are important for physical health
less is known about the relationship
between plant-based foods and cognitive
Health now in terms of preventing
Alzheimer's and other forms of actual
dementia there's data that those who
consume meat including poultry and fish
have two to three times the risk of
developing dementia compared with
vegetarians but what about just like
day-to-day function greater adherence to
more plant-based dietary pattern which
related to better performance on all
cognitive tasks researchers measured
one possible mechanism that could have
been thought to underlie the results is
body weight I mean plant-based diets
reduce BMI and lower BMI has been
associated with better cognitive
function but they still found a
connection between more plants and
better brain function even after
controlling for weight
another possible mechanism linking diet
and cognition is inflammation that's how
saturated fat impairs the memory of Lab
Rats through brain inflammation and
since fiber can be anti-inflammatory and
meet pro-inflammatory that may help
explain some of the effects of
plant-based diets on health and
cognition
the saturated fat connection appears to
extend to human cognition a systematic
review of meta-analysis covering nine
studies found that increased saturated
fat intake which is found mostly meat
Dairy and junk who associated with a 40
increased risk of cognitive impairment
and nearly 90 percent higher risk of
Alzheimer's disease so wait does that
mean if you put people on a low-carb
diet it impairs their brain function
yes it does a high fat diet not only
impairs the heart but also cognitive
function
men were randomized to just five days of
a high fat low carbohydrate diet or a
lower fat diet and on the low carb diet
cognitive tests showed they suffered
impaired attention speed and mood again
just within days conclusion raising the
level of fat in your blood not only
decreased energy production in the heart
but reduced cognition which suggests
that a high fat diet is detrimental to
the heart and brain now that we're
thinking the impaired energy production
may have accounted for the brain
dysfunction as well but oral glycotoxins
may also link high fat eating with a
loss of cognitive capacity
glycotoxins also known as advanced
glycation end products or ages our class
of oxidant stress promoting agents free
radical promoting agents implicated in
diabetes and aging including brain
injury due to Alzheimer's disease and
stroke the development of Alzheimer's
disease in the first place is thought to
involve the accumulation of these Ages
which encourage the formation and
deposition of the two Hallmarks of
Alzheimer's neurofibrillary Tangles and
amyloid plaques in the brain discovered
on autopsy but it's not just full-blown
dementia evidence suggests ages
contribute to cognitive decline in
general
dietary Advanced glycation end products
are associated with a decline in memory
and since modifying the levels of Ages
in the diet may be relatively easy these
preliminary results are just a simple
strategy to diminish cognitive
compromise what are the major sources of
dietary ages to stay away from meat
cooked using high dry heat such as in
broiling grilling frying and roasting
from my video the best diet for healthy
aging here is the list of all the most
Agee contaminated Foods
ages are not only associated with
getting Alzheimer's in the first place
but also the progression of Alzheimer's
disease as well as lower cognitive
performance in general as tracked
interestingly enough via skin
autofluorescence ages have a natural
fluorescence that you can pick up using
a special detector enabling a simple
non-invasive assessment of advanced
glycation and product accumulation in
the body the more meat you eat the more
the age skin autofluorescence you get
which then correlates with cognitive
impairment in fact one of these days
these fluorescent scanners may be
included in routine medical checkups
since meat is the main High age food it
should be no surprise that age skin
autofluorescence measurements are
significantly lower in those eating more
plant-based so the data suggests
reduction of food derived ages is
feasible and may provide an effective
treatment strategies for our epidemics
of Alzheimer's and metabolic disease
days
[Music]